<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sai Sanjay Yepuri</title>
    <description>Code and other things.
</description>
    <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 04:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 04:13:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Cloud on Your Desk</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Building a Cluster of Raspberry Pis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year ago at a hackathon an engineer had demoed what he called the “cloud on your desk.” Essentially it was  5 Raspberry Pis that were physically attached together on a frame with a network switch. Running on them was a software called OpenStack, a system designed to control compute, storage, and networking resources in large data centers that would be used by cloud applications. I found the compact device extremely interesting and felt that this was something I could do myself. But it wasn’t until earlier this year that I took up the challenge to build my own cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During spring break I decided to build a Pi cluster and have my own distributed computing test platform. I wanted to be able test various algorithms related to distributed systems (and maybe while it’s idle run a server or use it as a network share for our apartment). This was pretty different from the ideal of having the “cloud on your desk,” but it’ll be an interesting project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-build&quot;&gt;The Build&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I had looked online at other Pi clusters (such as this &lt;a href=&quot;https://makezine.com/projects/build-a-compact-4-node-raspberry-pi-cluster/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; on Makezine), I decided I needed around 4-5 Raspberry Pis, a USB charging hub, and a network switch. Most any USB hubs and network switches should do; here are the specific ones that I bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5x Raspberry Pi 3 B+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1x Anker 7 port USB Charging Hub&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1x Netgear FS108 8-port Network Switch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5x 6in. Ethernet Cables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5x 6in. MicroUSB Cables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5x 16GB microSD cards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then 3D printed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:1573414&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; stackable chassis for the Pis which I attached to the switch using a special permanent 3M tape. The end result was a little messy because I had run out of plastic towards the end of the print however the cluster was still functional. In fact this had allowed me to later borrow a friends Pi screen to attach to the top of the cluster (the cherry on top). This is how it turned out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pi-cluster-build.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the spring after I had assembled the components, I’ve been swamped by school work; the cluster has mostly been sitting idle on a shelf collecting dust. However last weekend the project got revived. I made it a goal that I complete the project and document the path I take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post about the cluster, I will install an operating system onto the Pis and configure the network so that they can all communicate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/the-cloud-on-your-desk</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/the-cloud-on-your-desk</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
